The Henry Darwin Didama MD Collection
Archives and Special Collections at the SUNY Upstate Health Sciences Library
The Henry Darwin Didama MD Collection
1842-1958
1842-1906
SUNY Upstate Medical University 766 Irving Avenue Syracuse, NY 13210
Didama, Henry D. (Henry Darwin), 1823-1905
.21 linear feet
This collection contains the papers of Henry Darwin Didama, who became a Professor of Clinical Medicine at the Syracuse University College of Medicine in 1872 and Dean of the College of Medicine beginning in 1888. The collection has five series: Writings, Printed Materials, Photographs, Subject Files, and Memorabilia.
FIC2017.0003
Biographical Note
Henry Darwin Didama (1823-1905) was born in Perryville on June 17, 1823. His father and grandfather, John and Simon Didama, came from Delft, Holland with the Holland Company to settle in Trenton, NY and both worked as doctors. Henry attended Cazenovia Seminary and was a teacher during the winter of 1840-1841. He began practicing medicine in the office of Doctor David A. Moore of Cazenovia and continued under Doctor Nelson A. Powers of Syracuse. He studied at the Geneva College of Medicine and the Albany Medical School, the latter of which he graduated from in 1846 at the age of 23. He then settled in Romulus, where he remained for 5 years and studied under Enos Smith Vail. At this time, he met and married Sarah Miller, the daughter of Honorable Sherman Miller. Henry came to Syracuse in 1851, and in 1874 he bought the Wescott homestead on South Salina Street and made that his office and home for the remainder of his life. The family had three children; Henry Darwin Jr., who died in infancy; Sherman, who died when a medical student; and Amelia, who married William M. Niven and completed a medical course at Syracuse and assisted her father, but died in 1893 from typhoid fever in Florida.
With the establishment of the Medical College in 1872, he was elected as Professor of Clinical Medicine, and in 1873, he was made Professor of the Principles and Practice of Medicine and Clinical Medicine, which he served as until his resignation in 1893. After the death of Dean Frederick Hyde in 1888, he was elected Dean of the College of Medicine and received the degree of LL.D. from Syracuse University that same year. In 1894, he was elected Trustee at Large of Syracuse University, which he served as until his death. In addition, he wrote under the nom de plume Amos Cottle about his observations of foreign customs and people in letters to the local press. He most notably served as president of the Onondaga County Medical Society, the Syracuse City Medical Society, the Central New York Medical Association, the Medical Society of the State of New York, the New York Medical Association, and the Syracuse Academy of Medicine, and Vice President of the American Medical Association before his death on October 4, 1905.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the papers of Henry Darwin Didama, who became a Professor of Clinical Medicine at the Syracuse University College of Medicine in 1872 and Dean of the College of Medicine beginning in 1888. There are five series in this collection.
Writings: this series contains the original and typed transcription of Henry Darwin Didama’s diary entitled “Private Journal of the Affairs du Vie, 1842-1852.”
Printed materials: these documents include printed materials from and about Henry Darwin Didama from 1875 to 1906.
Photographs: these materials are portrait photographs of Henry Darwin Didama and correspondence from 1944 on the donation of two portrait photographs from R.W.S. Vail of Albany, the grandchild of Enos Smith Vail of Romulus.
Subject Files: this contains one folder with information on Henry Darwin Didama.
Memorabilia: these documents consist of certifications, membership, and diplomas.
Arrangement of the Collection
The Henry Darwin Didama MD Collection has been arranged into five series.
Subject and Genre Headings
Didama, Henry D. (Henry Darwin), 1823-1905; Pierpont, John, 1785-1866; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874; Abolitionist; Agriculture; Anatomy; Chemistry; Democratic Party (U.S.); Dyspepsia; Equal Rights Party (N.Y.); Erie Canal (N.Y.); Influenza; Liberty Party (U.S.: 1840-1848); Marriage; Medical education; Midwifery; Millerite movement; Obstetrics; Political parties; Religion; Sex; Singing school; Slavery; Surgery; Temperance; Texas; Tobacco; Tuberculosis; Whig Party (U.S.); Geneva Medical College; Syracuse University. College of Medicine
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Inventory
- Writings
  - Private Journal of the Affairs du Vie, 1842-1852 (Box Box 1)
  - Digital Transcription (Box Digital Item # 2017.0168)
  - Typed Transcription, undated (Box Box 1)
- Printed Materials
  - The Model Physician. A Valedictory Address, Delivered in Wieting Hall, Syracuse, February 19th, 1875. By Henry D. Didama., 4 copies (Box Box 1)
  - Tubercular Consumption: Introduction to a Discussion at the New York State Medical Association, November, 1886. By H.D. Didama. (Box Box 1)
  - Tubercular Consumption: Is it Ever Inherited? Read at the Second Annual Meeting of the New York State Medical Association, November, 1885. By Henry D. Didama. (Box Box 1)
  - Anniversary Address, Before the Medical Society of the State of New York, At its Seventy-Fourth Annual Meeting, by H.D. Didama., 1880 (Box Box 1)
  - Henry Darwin Didama. By John L. Heffron. From the New York State Journal of Medicine, October, 1906. (Box Box 1)
  - Memoranda, Practical and Suggestive. (a) Early Aspiration in Pleuritis. (b) Mineral Waters, Crude and Refined. (c) Coughing Made Easy in Bronchiectasis. (d) The Insurance Sponge. By H.D. Didama., 1893 (Box Box 1)
  - Conservative Progress. First Annual Address to the New York State Medical Association, Delivered in New York, November 18, 1884, by Henry D. Didama. (Box Box 1)
  - Photocopy of Inaugural Address, Delivered February 3d, 1880, at the Opening of the Seventy-Fourth Annual Meeting. By the President, Henry Darwin Didama. From the Transactions of the Medical Society of the State of New York., undated (Box Box 1)
  - The Ideal Physician. By Henry D. Didama., 1904 (Box Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Portrait photographs of Henry Darwin Didama and correspondence from 1944 on the donation of two portrait photographs from R.W.S. Vail of Albany, the grandchild of Enos Smith Vail of Romulus., 1902; undated (Box Box 1, Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
- Subject Files
  - Documents concerning Henry Darwin Didama, including a typed partial bibliography of his writings from 1958, an undated article from the Medical Book News quoting Dr. Didama, a photocopy of a newspaper clipping on Dr. Didama’s funeral services, and a note to Miss Bond from Henry Darwin Didama to post a notice that surgery will be omitted from the second year so that the first and second year can focus on the fundamental branches and pathology and the third and fourth years can focus on the practical application., 1903 (Box Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Membership certifications to the New York State Medical Association, the British Medical Association, the Onondaga Medical Society, the Gynaecological Society of Boston, the New York State Medical Association, and the American Medical Association., 1869; 1877-1878; 1884-1886 (Box Box 1)
  - Certification of attendance for course the Surgical Diseases of Women in Boston from Horatio R. Storer with portrait photograph., 1868 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Albany Medical College diploma., 1846 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Certification of appointment as colonel of the 6th division of the National Guard in the state of New York., 1874 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Certification from the American Medical Association as representative to the International Medical Congress., 1884 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Certification as founder and fellow of the New York State Medical Association., 1884 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Ticket, invitation, program, and menu for dinner given in honor of Dean Henry Darwin Didama on the occasion of his fiftieth anniversary as a practitioner of medicine., 1897 (Box Box 1)